Jacob Rozran - US Citizen

DATA SCIENCE PRACTICE LEAD & ADJUNCT PROFESSOR OF DATA SCIENCE

1400 Maryland Ave. Havertown, PA 19083

□ (410) 231-9371 | ■ jacob.rozran@gmail.com | ♠ jakelearnsdatascience.com | ☑ jrozra200 | च jacob-rozran | ♥ StatsManPHL

Application Information

Title: Senior Technologist - IT Specialist (Policy and Planning) **Agency:** Consumer Financial Protection Bureau (CFPB)

Announcement Number: 22-CFPB-297-X

Grade Level: CN 71

Location: Remote (I reside in Havertown, PA)

Personal Summary _____

In addition to being a dad, uncle, & data guy, I am a data & technology professional with real-world experience in data science, advocacy, building and growing teams, project management, sales, consulting, and teaching. I am curious about the changing landscape of technology's impact on our lives and especially passionate about fair and ethical algorithms. My passion for data and statistics has also inspired me to become an Adjunct Professor of Data Science & Statistics, which has improved my ability to explain complex subjects to all levels of understanding.

Top Skills & Technologies_

METHODS	APPLICATIONS	LANGUAGES	DATABASES
Data Ethics	RStudio	SQL	PostgreSQL
Data Visualization	Jupyter Notebooks	R	Hive/Impala (Hadoop)
Data Analysis	Tableau/Metabase/Redash	Python	Athena (AWS)
Project Management	GitHub	Bash	SQL/mySQL/SQLite
People Leadership	MS Office Suite	HTML	Neo4J

Experience _____

CIVICACTIONS

Title: Data Science Practice Lead (Remote)

Company Location: 3527 Mt. Diablo Blvd., Unit 269, Lafayette, CA

Supervisor (please do not contact): Bill Ogilvie, Vice President of Sales, (202) 415-0947

Dates of Employment: February 22, 2021 - Present **Hours per Week:** Full-time (40 hours per week)

Salary: \$165,000 (Other benefits not included in salary number)

Duties and Accomplishments:

- Building a Data Science Practice Area with > \$1MM revenue after 12 months; personally focused on data science, people management and coaching, sales, marketing, and project management.
- For various clients at the Centers of Medicare and Medicaid (CMS):
 - Leveraging Natural Language Processing (NLP) in the creation, evaluation, and summarization of System Security Plans (SSPs) to optimize the Authority to Operate (ATO) process. Technologies used: Python, R, Rmd, GitHub, GitHub Pages.
 - Analyzing AWS usage data to investigate misuse of resources, forecast annual usage, identify inefficiencies, and alert on anomalies. Technologies used: R, Shiny Dashboards, AWS Athena, GitHub.
 - Using graph analysis and NLP to identify related documents for enhanced search capabilities. Technologies used: R, Rmd, GitHub.
- One of five members of the company's Diversity, Equity, Inclusion, and Accessibility (DEIA) team.
 - Responsible for helping improve the company's DEIA practices, including analyzing demographic data, designing surveys to understand company feeling about DEIA, and identifying and improving company policy to be more inclusive. Technologies used: R, Rmd, CultureAmp, GitHub.

VILLANOVA UNIVERSITY

Title: Adjunct Professor of Data Science and Statistics **University Location:** 800 Lancaster Avenue, Villanova, PA

Supervisor: Dr. Jesse Frey, Department of Mathematics and Statistics Chairperson, (610) 519-4850

Dates of Employment: August 10, 2020 - Present

Hours per Week: Part-time (~15 hours per week during the semester)

Salary: \$8,700 (\$1,450 per credit hour)

Duties and Accomplishments:

• Build the syllabus, lectures, assignments, projects, and tests for undergraduate Data Science, Intro to Statistics, and Intro to Statistics for Biology courses.

• Advise and mentor students by writing recommendations for various programs, helping guide studies for real-world success after graduation, and providing assistance through the stresses of university life.

NEW AMERICA

Title: Public Interest Technology - University Network (PIT-UN) Evaluation Committee Member (Remote)

Company Location: 740 15th Street NW, Suite 900, Washington, DC

Supervisor: NA

Dates of Employment: May 27, 2022 - July 18, 2022

Hours per Week: Part-time (~5 hours per week during the evaluation period)

Salary: \$650

Duties and Accomplishments:

• Evaluate proposals seeking funding to educate students who can better apply technical understanding and practice to questions of individual rights, justice, social welfare, and the public good, particularly for those members of our society least well served historically and today by existing systems and policies

SOCURE

Title: Solutions Consultant (Remote)

Company Location: 885 Tahoe Blvd Suite 11, Incline Village, NV

Supervisor: Garient Evans, Vice President of Growth, (858) 945-3515 (No longer at Socure)

Dates of Employment: January 13, 2020 - February 12, 2021

Hours per Week: Full-time (40 hours per week)

Salary: \$150,000 + Sales Incentive (paid quarterly up to \$75,000)

Duties and Accomplishments:

- Technical expert on fraud prevention, Know Your Customer (KYC)/Customer Identification Program (CIP), Socure product modules, data science, statistics, and data visualization in support of the sales and onboarding processes.
- Created custom proof-of-concept (POC) analyses for prospective customers showing the value of Socure versus their current solution(s).
- Served as the Growth Team's subject matter expert (SME) on data science, creating educational documents and presentations on challenging topics like Area Under the Curve (AUC), false positives, and other model evaluation criteria.
- Worked with the Marketing Team to create content for the Socure Blog on machine learning techniques.
- · Member of the DEI team.

Сомсаѕт

Title: Manager of Data Analytics - Xfinity Mobile Risk Management **Company Location:** 1701 John F. Kennedy Blvd., Philadelphia, PA

Supervisor: Mike McCabe, Executive Director of Credit Risk Management, (913) 485-3592 (No longer at Comcast)

Dates of Employment: March 20, 2017 - January 10, 2020

Hours per Week: Full-time (40 hours per week)

Salary: ~\$120,000 (Other benefits not included in salary number)

Duties and Accomplishments:

- Designed, built, deployed, maintained, and monitored a fraud decision making tool that combines custom feature creation, statistical and business rules, and predictive models, which, in large part, is responsible for a decrease in month-over-month fraud losses by 92% in 2018. Technologies Used: R, Python, Random Forest, Cloudera Hadoop (Impala), OracleDB, Tableau, Rmd, and GitHub.
- Led and managed the data analytics and engineering team for Xfinity Mobile Credit Risk Management, including hiring and training of staff analysts and engineers, collaborating with and providing analysis for stakeholders, and tracking and prioritizing all team tasking.
- Provide coaching, leadership, and mentorship to all analysts on the Xfinity Mobile Risk Management team.

COMCAST

Title: Senior Data Analyst - Internet Services Engineering

Company Location: 1701 John F. Kennedy Blvd., Philadelphia, PA

Supervisor: Tom Payne, Senior Manager of Insights and Analytics, (202) 210-2120

Dates of Employment: September 15, 2014 - March 17, 2017

Hours per Week: Full-time (40 hours per week)

Salary: ~\$95,000 (Other benefits not included in salary number)

Duties and Accomplishments:

- Designed and built predictive models, which improved compromised user account detection times and discovery accuracy this work was presented internally along with several internal blog posts about the effort. Technologies Used: R, Splunk, Logistic Regression, and Microsoft Excel.
- Used statistical methods to discover and automate the detection of anomalies.
- Created forecasts of user base growth and project completion.

COMCAST

Title: Project Manager - Messaging Application Engineering **Company Location:** 1701 John F. Kennedy Blvd., Philadelphia, PA

Supervisor: Jordan Rosenwald, Director of Software Development & Engineering, (856) 448-4767

Dates of Employment: April 22, 2013 - September 12, 2014

Hours per Week: Full-time (40 hours per week)

Salary: ~\$72,000 (Other benefits not included in salary number)

Duties and Accomplishments:

- Served as a Project Manager and ScrumMaster for the Messaging Application Engineering (MAE) team, responsible for Residential Voicemail and Email Engineering teams.
- Obtained my Project Management Professional (PMP) and Certified ScrumMaster (CSM) certifications.
- Instituted and evangelized Scrum on both the email and voicemail teams, migrating from a hybrid of waterfall and Kanban, which led to higher team productivity, better communication across teams from development through deployment to production, and improved interaction with our product owners.

BOOZ ALLEN HAMILTON (BAH)

Title: Senior Consultant & Implementation Manager - National Institutes of Health (NIH) Eunice Kennedy Shriver National Institute of Child Health and Human Services (NICHD) National Children's Study (NCS) Main Study Information Management Systems Project

Company Location: 8283 Greensboro Drive, McLean, VA **Project Location:** One Preserve Parkway, Rockville, MD

Supervisor: Christian Sauter, Lead Associate, (856) 625-5332 (no longer with BAH)

Dates of Employment: November 8, 2010 - April 12, 2013

Hours per Week: Full-time (40 hours per week)

Salary: ~\$50,000 (Other benefits not included in salary number)

Duties and Accomplishments:

 Served as the Implementation Manager and Site Administrator for the National Children's Study (NCS) Portal, a Microsoft SharePoint 2010 web application, the NCS Application Homepage, and NCS Password Self Service.

BOOZ ALLEN HAMILTON (BAH)

Title: Consultant & Financial Analyst/Project Manager - NAVAIR Radio Information Systems (RIS) Project

Company Location: 8283 Greensboro Drive, McLean, VA

Project Location: Naval Outlying Field Webster, St. Inigoes, MD

Supervisor: NA

Dates of Employment: November 2, 2009 - November 5, 2010

Hours per Week: Full-time (40 hours per week)

Salary: \$42,000 (Other benefits not included in salary number)

Duties and Accomplishments:

 Developed a financial tracking system for client, which allowed key stakeholders to view current and projected funding over the lifetime of the contract.

Volunteer

GOVERN FOR AMERICA

Title: Resident Data Science Expert (Remote)

Company Location: 107 North Salem Road, Katonah, NY

Supervisor: Talita Elizeu, Alumni & Community Engagement Director, (617) 435-9200

Dates of Involvement: April 8, 2022 - Present

Hours per Week: Part-time **Duties and Accomplishments:**

• Provide training and mentorship in data science, data visualization, and data ethics for GFA fellows.

DATA JAWN CONFERENCE

Title: Organizer (Remote)

Supervisor: Dan Larson, Founder and Lead, (484) 560-5753

Dates of Involvement: April 20, 2019 - Present

Hours per Week: Part-time **Duties and Accomplishments:**

> Assist in promotion, speaker selection, and day-of-event logistics for the Data Jawn, a Philadelphia data conference highlighting the great work of our local data commnuity.

MONTGOMERY COUNTY PUBLIC DEFENDER

Title: Data Analyst (Remote)

Company Location: P.O. Box 311, Norristown, PA

Supervisor: Dean Beer, Chief Public Defender, (610) 246-7613 (no longer at Public Defender's office)

Dates of Involvement: May 9, 2016 - June 5, 2017

Hours per Week: Part-time **Duties and Accomplishments:**

> Assisted Montgomery County Public Defender to define an analytics strategy to support competitive salaries and fair defence for all Montgomery County residents; created, built, and maintained advanced analysis.

Education

VILLANOVA UNVERSITY

University Location: 800 Lancaster Avenue, Villanova, PA **Degree Awarded:** Masters of Science in Applied Statistics

Date Received: May 12, 2017

GPA: 3.53

DREXEL UNVERSITY

University Location: 3141 Chestnut Street, Philadelphia, PA **Degree Awarded:** Bachelors of Science in Business & Engineering

Date Received: June 5, 2009

GPA: 3.22